(Music)
(موسيقى)
♪ It's all there in gospels ♪
♪ كل شيء مذكور بالبشارات ♪
♪A Magdalene girl comes to pay her respects ♪
♪ ماجدلينا الفتاة جاءت مرحبة ♪
♪ But her mind is awhirl ♪
♪ لكن عقلها كان يدور كالدوامة ♪
♪ When she finds the tomb empty ♪
♪ عندما وجدت القبر خاليا ♪
♪ Straw had been rolled ♪
♪ والقش ملفوفا ♪
♪ Not a sign of a corpse ♪
♪ لا أثر لجثة ♪
♪ In the dark and the cold ♪
♪ في الظلام والبرد ♪
♪ When she reaches the door ♪
♪ وهي تمضي إلى الباب ♪
♪ Sees an unholy sight ♪
♪ ترى مشهدا شيطانيا ♪
♪ There's a solitary figure and a halo of light ♪
♪ ثمة شخص وحيد وهالة من الضوء ♪
♪ He just carries on floating past Calvary Hill ♪
♪ ظل طافيا إلى ما بعد كالفاري هيل ♪
♪ In an Almighty hurry ♪
♪ في عجلة مقدسة ♪
♪ Aye, but she might catch him still ♪
♪ نعم، ولكنها ما تزال تستطيع اللحاق به ♪
♪ Tell me where are you gone, Lord ♪
♪ أخبرني إلى أين أنت ذاهبٌ، سيدي ♪
♪ And why in such haste? ♪
♪ ولم بتلك العجلة؟ ♪
♪ Oh don't hinder me, woman ♪
♪ لا تعطليني يا امرأة ♪
♪ I've no time to waste ♪
♪ ليس لدي وقت لأضيعه ♪
♪ For they're launching a boat on the morrow at noon ♪
♪ لأنهم سيدشنون قاربا عند ظهيرة الغد ♪
♪ And I have to be there before daybreak ♪
♪ ولا بد أن أكون هناك قبل انقضاء اليوم ♪
♪ Oh I cannot be missing ♪
♪ لا يمكنني أن أفوته ♪
♪ The lads'll expect me ♪
♪ الفتية بانتظاري هناك ♪
♪ Why else would the Good Lord Himself resurrect me? ♪
♪ لأي شيء غير هذا بعثني الرب العظيم؟ ♪
♪ For nothing'll stop me. I have to prevail ♪
♪ لا شئ سيوقفني. يجب أن أنتصر ♪
♪ Through the teeth of this tempest ♪
♪ من بين أنياب هذه العاصفة ♪
♪ In the mouth of a gale ♪
♪ في فم إعصار ♪
♪ May the angels protect me ♪
♪ فلتحمني الملائكة ♪
♪ If all else should fail ♪
♪ لو كان مقدرا فشل الجميع ♪
♪ And the last ship sails ♪
♪ وتبحر آخر سفينة ♪
♪ Oh the roar of the chains ♪
♪ يا هدير السلاسل ♪
♪ And the cracking of timbers ♪
♪ وتشقق الأخشاب ♪
♪ The noise at the end of the world in your ears ♪
♪ تسمع الضجة عند نهاية العالم في أذنيك ♪
♪ As a mountain of steel makes its way to the sea ♪
♪ كجبل من الصلب يشق طريقه إلى البحر ♪
♪ And the last ship sails ♪
♪ وتبحر آخر سفينة ♪
So I was born and raised
لقد ولدت ونشأت
in the shadow of a shipyard
بمقربة من حوض بناء سفن
in a little town on the northeast coast of England.
في بلدة صغيرة على الساحل الشمالي الشرقي لإنجلترا.
Some of my earliest memories
بعض من ذكريات الطفولة
are of giant ships
تدور حول السفن العملاقة
blocking the end of my street,
وهي تحجب نهاية شارعي،
as well as the sun, for a lot of the year.
وكذلك الشمس، لمعظم السنة.
Every morning as a child,
كطفل وفي صبيحة كل يوم،
I'd watch thousands of men walk down that hill
كنت أشاهد الآلاف من الرجال ينزلون من ذلك التل
to work in the shipyard.
للعمل في حوض بناء السفن.
I'd watch those same men
كنت أشاهد نفس أولئك الرجال
walking back home every night.
عائدين أدراجهم عند كل مساء.
It has to be said, the shipyard was not
لا بد من القول، أن حوض بناء السفن لم يكن
the most pleasant place to live next door to,
المكان الأكثر بهجة للعيش بقربه،
or indeed work in.
أو حتى العمل فيه.
The shipyard was noisy, dangerous,
كان حوض بناء السفن مزعجا وخطيرا
highly toxic,
وشديد السمية،
with an appalling health and safety record.
مع سجل صحة وسلامة مروع.
Despite that, the men and women
رغم ذلك، كان الرجال والنساء
who worked on those ships
الذين عملوا على تلك السفن
were extraordinarily proud of the work they did,
يشعرون بفخر استثنائي تجاه عملهم،
and justifiably so.
ولذلك ما يبرره.
Some of the largest vessels
إن بعض أكبر السفن
ever constructed on planet Earth
التي بنيت على كوكب الأرض
were built right at the end of my street.
تم بناؤها عند نهاية شارعي.
My grandfather had been a shipwright,
كان جدي بنَّاء سفن،
and as a child,
وكطفل،
as there were few other jobs in the town,
باعتبار عدم توفر وظائف أخرى في المدينة،
I would wonder with some anxiety
كنت أتساءل بشيء من القلق
whether that would be my destiny too.
إن كان ذلك سيكون مستقبلي أيضا.
I was fairly determined that it wouldn't be.
كنت مصمما بشدة أن ذلك لن يحدث.
I had other dreams,
كانت لي أحلام أخرى،
not necessarily practical ones,
ليست عملية بالضرورة،
but at the age of eight,
ولكن في عمر الثامنة،
I was bequeathed a guitar.
ورثت غيتارا.
It was a battered old thing
كان شيئا قديما متداعيا
with five rusty strings, and was out of tune,
به خمسة أوتار صدئة وغير مدوزن،
but quickly I learned to play it
ولكن سرعان ما تعلمت العزف عليه
and realized that I'd found a friend for life,
ثم أدركت أني قد عثرت على صديق عمري،
an accomplice, a co-conspirator
متواطئ و شريك
in my plan to escape from this surreal
ضمن خطتي لكي أهرب من هذا
industrial landscape.
المشهد الصناعي العجيب.
Well, they say if you dream something hard enough,
حسنا، يقولون إن حلمت بشيء بشكل صادق
it will come to pass.
فسيأتي إليك.
Either that, or I was extremely lucky,
إما ذلك، أو أني كنت محظوظا للغاية،
but this was my dream.
ولكن كان هذا حلمي.
I dreamt I would leave this town,
حلمت بأني سأغادر هذه البلدة،
and just like those ships,
بالضبط كتلك السفن،
once they were launched, I'd never come back.
في حال تم إطلاقها، لن أعودَ مجددا.
I dreamt I'd become a writer of songs,
حلمت بأني سأصبح كاتب أغان،
that I would sing those songs
وسأغني تلك الأغاني
to vast numbers of people all over the world,
لعدد ضخم من الناس حول العالم،
that I would be paid extravagant amounts of money,
وسيُدفع لي مبالغ ضخمة من المال،
that I'd become famous,
وسأصبح مشهورا،
that I'd marry a beautiful woman,
وسأتزوج امرأة جميلة،
have children, raise a family,
وأصبح أبا وأرعى أسرة،
buy a big house in the country,
وأشتري منزلا كبيرا في البلاد،
keep dogs, grow wine,
وأقتني كلابا، وأعصر النبيذ،
have rooms full of Grammy Awards,
وأمتلك غرفة مليئة بجوائز الغرامي،
platinum discs, and what have you.
وأقراص بلاتينة، ماذا تضيفون.
So far, so good, right? (Laughter)
حتى الآن، لا بأس، أليس كذلك؟ (ضحك)
And then one day, the songs stopped coming,
ثم ذات يوم، نضبت الأغاني.
and while you've suffered from periods
وفي حال عانيتم من فترات
of writer's block before, albeit briefly,
الشلل الإبداعي للكاتب ولو لفترة وجيزة
this is something chronic.
فهذا شيء مزمن.
Day after day, you face a blank page,
يوما بعد يوم، تجلس أمام ورقة فارغة
and nothing's coming.
ولا شيء جديد.
And those days turned to weeks, and weeks to months,
وهكذا تصبح الأيام شهورا والشهور سنينا،
and pretty soon those months
وعما قريب تصبح الشهور
have turned into years
سنينا
with very little to show for your efforts. No songs.
مع القليل جدا مقابل مجهوداتك، لا أغاني تُذكر.
So you start asking yourself questions.
فتبدأ بالتساؤل.
What have I done to offend the gods
بماذا أسأت للآلهة
that they would abandon me so?
حتى تتخلى عني هكذا؟
Is the gift of songwriting taken away
هل انتزعت عني موهبة كتابة الأغاني
as easily as it seems to have been bestowed?
بالسهولة التي أعطيتها؟
Or perhaps there's a more --
أو ربما يوجد المزيد--
a deeper psychological reason.
سببٌ نفسيٌ أعمقْ.
It was always a Faustian pact anyway.
دائما ما كان الأمر بمثابة ميثاق مع الشيطان
You're rewarded for revealing
فأنت تكافأ مقابل الكشف
your innermost thoughts,
عن عميق أفكارك
your private emotions on the page
مشاعرك الخاصة على الورق
for the entertainment of others,
في سبيل الترفيه عن الآخرين،
for the analysis, the scrutiny of others,
بغرض التحليل و التمحيص لفائدة الغير،
and perhaps you've given enough
وربما تتخلى عن جزء كافٍ
of your privacy away.
من خصوصيتك.
And yet, if you look at your work,
فإذا نظرت إلى أعمالك الخاصة،
could it be argued that your best work
يمكن القول أن أفضل أعمالك
wasn't about you at all,
لم تكن تدور حولك مطلقا،
it was about somebody else?
بل كانت عن شخص آخر؟
Did your best work occur
هل حدث أن كانت أفضل أعمالك
when you sidestepped your own ego
عندما نحيت الأنا الخاصة بك جانبا
and you stopped telling your story,
و توقفت عن حكي قصتك
but told someone else's story,
لكي تحكي عن شخص آخر،
someone perhaps without a voice,
شخص ما ربما دون صوت يعبر عنه،
where empathetically, you stood in his shoes
حيث وضعت نفسك متضامنا في مكانه
for a while or saw the world through his eyes?
لمدة أو رأيت العالم من خلال عينيه؟
Well they say, write what you know.
حسنا، يقولون اكتب عن ما تعرف.
If you can't write about yourself anymore,
إن لم تعد قادرا على الكتابة عن نفسك مجددا،
then who do you write about?
فعن ماذا تكتب؟
So it's ironic that the landscape
لذلك فهو لشيء مثير للسخرية أن نفس المشهد
I'd worked so hard to escape from,
الذي عملت جاهدا للهروب منه
and the community that I'd more or less abandoned
والمجتمع الذي كثيرا كان أو قليلا هجرته
and exiled myself from
ونفيت نفسي منه
should be the very landscape,
أن يكون المشهد الأكثر
the very community I would have to return to
والمجتمع الأكثر ضرورة أن أعود إليه
to find my missing muse.
كي أجد متعتي المفقودة.
And as soon as I did that,
وحالما فعلت ذلك،
as soon as I decided to honor the community
عندما قررت أن أشرِّف المجتمع
I came from and tell their story,
الذي أتيت منه وأحكي عن قصتهم،
that the songs started to come thick and fast.
بدأت الأغاني تأتي سراعا وبغزارة.
I've described it as a kind of projectile vomiting,
لقد وصفت ذلك كنوع من قذيفة تقيؤ،
a torrent of ideas, of characters, of voices,
سيل من الأفكار، من الشخصيات، من الأصوات،
of verses, couplets, entire songs
من الآيات، مقاطع وأغاني كاملة
almost formed whole,
تشكلت بالكامل تقريبا،
materialized in front of me
متجسدة أمامي
as if they'd been bottled up inside me
كما لو أنها كانت مكبوتة بداخلي
for many, many years.
لسنين عدة.
One of the first things I wrote was just a list of names
من أوائل ما كتبت كان عبارة عن قائمة من الأسماء
of people I'd known,
لأناس عرفتهم من قبل.
and they become characters
أصبحوا شخصيات
in a kind of three-dimensional drama,
في شكل دراما ثلاثية الأبعاد،
where they explain who they are, what they do,
حيث يعبرون عن ماهيتهم، ماذا يفعلون،
their hopes and their fears for the future.
أحلامهم و مخاوفهم من المستقبل.
This is Jackie White.
هذا جاكي وايت.
He's the foreman of the shipyard.
رئيس عمال حوض بناء السفن.
My name is Jackie White,
اسمي جاكي وايت،
and I'm foreman of the yard,
وأنا رئيس عمال الساحة
and you don't mess with Jackie on this quayside.
فلا تعبث مع جاكي على رصيف الميناء هذا.
I'm as hard as iron plate,
أنا قوي مثل صحن حديدي،
woe betide you if you're late
الويل لك إن كنت متأخرا
when we have to push a boat out on the spring tide.
إذا صادف ذلك دفع قارب على المد الربيعي.
Now you can die and hope for heaven,
فستموت وتتمنى الجنة،
but you need to work your shift,
ولكن يتوجب عليك إنهاء ورديتك،
and I'd expect you all to back us to the hilt,
وأتوقع دعمكم جميعا لنا،
for if St. Peter at his gate
في حال تواجد القديس بطرس عند بوابته
were to ask you why you're late,
وسألكم لماذا أنتم متأخرون،
why, you tell him that you had to get a ship built.
أخبروه أنه كان يتوجب عليكم بناء سفينة.
We build battleships and cruisers
فنحن نبني بوارج وطرادات
for Her Majesty the Queen,
لصاحبة الجلالة الملكة،
supertankers for Onassis, and all the classes in between,
الناقلات العملاقة لأوناسيس، وكل ما بين ذلك،
We built the greatest ship in tonnage
قمنا ببناء أكبر سفينة من حيث الحمولة
what the world has ever seen
شهدها العالم من قبل
♪ And the only life worth knowing is in the shipyard ♪
♪ لا حياة تستحق أن تعاش مثل الحياة في حوض بناء السفن ♪
♪ Steel in the stockyard, iron in the soul ♪
♪ الصُّلب في الحظيرة والحديد يملأ النفوس ♪
♪ Would conjure up a ship ♪
♪ سوف تستحضر سفينة ♪
♪ Where there used to be a hull ♪
♪ حيث كان هناك هيكل سفينة ♪
♪ And we don't know what we'll do ♪
♪ ولا نعرف ماذا سنفعل ♪
♪ If this yard gets sold ♪
♪ في حال بيعت هذه الساحة ♪
♪ For the only life worth knowing is in the shipyard ♪
♪ لا حياة تستحق أن تعاش مثل الحياة في حوض بناء السفن ♪
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So having decided to write about other people
لذلك كان قرار الكتابة عن الآخرين
instead of myself,
بدلا عن نفسي،
a further irony is that sometimes you reveal
مفارقة أخرى هي أنك في بعض الأحيان تكشف
more about yourself than you'd ever intended.
المزيد عن مكنوناتك أكثر من ما كنت تنوي.
This song is called "Dead Man's Boots,"
هذه الأغنية تسمى "أحذية الرجل الميت"،
which is an expression
هي عبارة عن تعبير
which describes how difficult it is to get a job;
يصف صعوبة الحصول على عمل؛
in other words, you'd only get a job in the shipyard
بمعنى آخر، لن تحصل على عمل في الحوض
if somebody else died.
إلا بوفاة شخص آخر.
Or perhaps your father could finagle you
أو ربما أن يتوسط لك والدك
an apprenticeship at the age of 15.
كتلميذ في سن الخامسة عشر.
But sometimes a father's love can be misconstrued
لكن في بعض الأحيان حب الأب يمكن أن يساء فهمه
as controlling,
على أنه تحكم،
and conversely, the scope of his son's ambition
وعلى العكس، فإن نطاق طموح ابنه
can seem like some pie-in-the-sky fantasy.
قد يبدو مثل بعض خيال لا معنى له.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
♪ You see these work boots in my hands ♪
♪ أترى أحذية العمل هذه في يدي ♪
♪ They'll probably fit you now, my son ♪
♪ من المحتمل أنها ستناسبك الآن يا بني ♪
♪ Take them, they're a gift from me ♪
♪ خذهما فهما هدية مني ♪
♪ Why don't you try them on? ♪
♪ لما لا تجربهما؟ ♪
♪ It would do your old man good to see ♪
♪ سيكون شيئا جميلا لوالدك أن يراك ♪
♪ You walking in these boots one day ♪
♪ تمشي بهذين الحذاءين يوما ما ♪
♪ And take your place among the men ♪
♪ وتحتل مكانك بين الرجال ♪
♪ Who work upon the slipway ♪
♪ الذين يعملون على الدعامة ♪
♪ These dead man's boots, though they're old and curled ♪
♪ أحذية الرجل الميت هذه رغم أنها قديمة ومجعدة ♪
♪ When a fellow needs a job and a place in the world ♪
♪ عندما يحتاج رفيق إلى عمل ومكان في هذا العالم ♪
♪ And it's time for a man to put down roots ♪
♪ فقد حان الوقت أن يضرب الرجل بجذوره في الأرض ♪
♪ And walk to the river in his old man's boots ♪
♪ وأن يسير الى النهر مرتديا أحذية الرجل العجوز ♪
♪ He said, "I'm dying, son, and asking ♪
♪ قال، "بني، أنا أحتضر وأطلب منك ♪
♪ That you do one final thing for me ♪
♪ أن تسدي لي خدمة أخيرة ♪
♪ You're barely but a sapling, and you think that you're a tree ♪
♪ أنت بالكاد شتلة، وتظن نفسك شجرة ♪
♪ If you need a seed to prosper ♪
♪ إن احتجت بذورا كي تزدهر ♪
♪ You must first put down some roots ♪
♪ فلا بد أن تضع بعض الجذور أولا ♪
♪ Just one foot then the other in ♪
♪ القدم الأولى ثم التي تليها في ♪
♪ These dead man's boots" ♪
♪ أحذية الرجل الميت هذه ♪
♪ These dead man's boots, though they're old and curled ♪
♪ أحذية الرجل الميت هذه رغم إنها قديمة ومجعدة ♪
♪ When a fellow needs a job and a place in the world ♪
♪ عندما يحتاج رجل إلى عمل ومكان في هذا العالم ♪
♪ And it's time for a man to put down roots ♪
♪ فقد حان الوقت أن يضرب الرجل بجذوره في الأرض ♪
♪ And walk to the river in his old man's boots ♪
♪ وأن يسير الى النهر مرتديا أحذية الرجل العجوز ♪
♪ I said, "Why in the hell would I do that? ♪
♪ قلت، "لماذا بحق الجحيم أفعل ذلك؟ ♪
♪ Why would I agree?" ♪
♪ لم يتوجب علي الموافقة؟" ♪
♪ When his hand was all that I'd received ♪
♪ عندما كانت يده هي كل ما حصلت عليه ♪
♪ As far as I remember ♪
♪ حسب ما أذكر ♪
♪ It's not as if he'd spoiled me with his kindness ♪
♪ ليس الأمر أنه أفسدني بعطفه ♪
♪ Up to then, you see ♪
♪ حتى ذلك الحين، ترى ♪
♪ I'd a plan of my own and I'd quit this place ♪
♪ إن لي خطتي الخاصة وسأغادر هذا المكان ♪
♪ When I came of age September ♪
♪ عندما أصبح في عمر سبتمبر ♪
♪ These dead man's boots know their way down the hill ♪
♪ أحذية الرجل الميت هذه تعرف طريقها جيدا أسفل التل ♪
♪ They could walk there themselves, and they probably will ♪
♪ تستطيع أن تذهب الى هناك بنفسها، وقد تفعل ♪
♪ I've plenty of choices, I've plenty other routes ♪
♪ لدي خيارات عدة وطرق أخرى عدة ♪
♪ And you'll never see me walking in these dead man's boots ♪
♪ وسوف لن تراني أبدا أرتدي أحذية الرجل الميت هذه ♪
♪ What was it made him think ♪
♪ ما الذي جعله يظن ♪
♪ I'd be happy ending up like him ♪
♪ أني سأكون سعيدا لو انتهى بي الأمر مثله ♪
♪ When he'd hardly got two halfpennies left ♪
♪ عندما بالكاد يحصل على بنسين ونصف ♪
♪ Or a broken pot to piss in? ♪
♪ أو وعاء مكسور ليقضي فيه حاجته ♪
♪ He wanted this same thing for me ♪
♪ لقد أراد لي نفس المصير ♪
♪ Was that his final wish? ♪
♪ هل كانت تلك آخر أمانيه؟ ♪
♪ He said, "What the hell are you gonna do?" ♪
♪ قال، "ماذا أنت فاعل بحق الجحيم؟ ♪
♪ I said, "Anything but this!" ♪
♪ فقلت، "أي شيء غير هذا!" ♪
♪ These dead man's boots know their way down the hill ♪
♪ أحذية الرجل الميت هذه تعرف طريقها جيدا أسفل التل ♪
♪ They can walk there themselves and they probably will ♪
♪ تستطيع أن تذهب الى هناك بنفسها، وقد تفعل ♪
♪ But they won't walk with me ‘cause I'm off the other way ♪
♪ ولكنها لن تصحبني لأني سأسلك مسارا آخر ♪
♪ I've had it up to here, I'm gonna have my say ♪
♪ إلى هنا وكفى، فأنا لي رأي آخر ♪
♪ When all you've got left is that cross on the wall ♪
♪ كل ما تبقى لك هو ذلك الصليب على الجدار ♪
♪ I want nothing from you, I want nothing at all ♪
♪ لا أريد منك شيئا، لا أريد شيئا على الإطلاق ♪
♪ Not a pension, nor a pittance, when your whole life is through ♪
♪ لا معاش ولا مبلغ زهيد، عندما تكون حياتك كلها هكذا ♪
♪ Get this through your head, I'm nothing like you ♪
♪ احلم، فأنا لست مثلك ♪
♪ I'm done with all the arguments, there'll be no more disputes ♪
♪ أنا انتهيت من جميع الحجج، سوف لن يكون هناك المزيد من الخلافات ♪
♪ And you'll die before you see me in your dead man's boots ♪
♪ وسوف تموت من غير أن تراني أرتدي أحذية رجلك الميت ♪
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.
So whenever they'd launch a big ship,
حسنا كلما دشنوا سفينة كبيرة،
they would invite some dignitary up from London
كانوا يستدعون بعض الأعيان من لندن
on the train to make a speech,
على متن القطار ليلقوا كلمة،
break a bottle of champagne over the bows,
ثم يكسرون زجاج الشمبانيا رميا بالأسهم،
launch it down the slipway
ثم ينزلون السفينة من على المزلقان
into the river and out to sea.
إلى النهر ومنه إلى عرض البحر.
Occasionally on a really important ship,
أحيانا حين تكون هناك سفينة مهمة،
they'd get a member of the royal family to come,
يدعون أحد أفراد العائلة المالكة،
Duke of Edinburgh, Princess Anne or somebody.
دوق إدنبره أو الأميرة آن أو أحد ما.
And you have to remember, it wasn't that long ago
ويجب أن تتذكروا، لم يكن ذلك منذ زمن بعيد
that the royal family in England
أن العائلة المالكة في إنجلترا
were considered to have magical healing powers.
كان يُعتقد أنها تتمتع بقوى شفاء سحرية
Sick children were held up in crowds
حيث كان يتم رفع الأطفال المرضى من بين الحشود
to try and touch the cloak
في محاولة للمس عباءة
of the king or the queen to cure them
الملك أو الملكة أملا في الشفاء
of some terrible disease.
من بعض الأمراض الفظيعة.
It wasn't like that in my day, but we still got very excited.
لم يكن نفس الشيء في أيامي، ولكن ما زلنا نشعر بالإثارة.
So it's a launch day, it's a Saturday,
إذا فهو يوم التدشين، يوم السبت،
and my mother has dressed me up in my Sunday best.
ألبستني أمي أزهى حللي.
I'm not very happy with her.
لم أكن سعيدا بذلك.
All the kids are out in the street,
كان كل الأطفال في الشارع،
and we have little Union Jacks to wave,
وكان لدينا بعض الأعلام الصغيرة نلوح بها،
and at the top of the hill,
وهناك على قمة التل،
there's a motorcycle cortege appears.
يظهر موكب من الدراجات النارية.
In the middle of the motorcycles,
وفي منتصف الدراجات النارية،
there's a big, black Rolls-Royce.
كانت هناك سيارة رولز رويس سوداء كبيرة.
Inside the Rolls-Royce is the Queen Mother.
بداخلها الملكة الأم.
This is a big deal.
هذا أمر عظيم.
So the procession is moving
كان الموكب يتقدم
at a stately pace down my street,
بوتيرة مهيبة أسفل شارعنا،
and as it approaches my house,
وبينما يقترب من بيتي،
I start to wave my flag vigorously,
بدأت ألوح بالعلم بحماس،
and there is the Queen Mother.
وهناك كانت الملكة الأم.
I see her, and she seems to see me.
أراها ويبدو أنها تراني.
She acknowledges me. She waves, and she smiles.
تتعرف عليّ. تلوح بيدها ثم تبتسم.
And I wave my flag even more vigorously.
وحينها ألوح بعلمي بنشاط أكثر.
We're having a moment,
أتيحت لنا الفرصة،
me and the Queen Mother.
أنا والملكة الأم.
She's acknowledged me.
تعرفت عليّ.
And then she's gone.
ثم ذهبت.
Well, I wasn't cured of anything.
حسنا، لم أكن أتعالج من أي شيء.
It was the opposite, actually.
بل كان الأمر عكس ذلك في الواقع.
I was infected.
لقد أصِبت.
I was infected with an idea.
أصابتي فكرة.
I don't belong in this street.
أنا لا أنتمي لهذا الشارع.
I don't want to live in that house.
لا أريد أن أعيش في ذلك المنزل.
I don't want to end up in that shipyard.
لا أريد أن ينتهي بي المطاف في حوض بناء السفن.
I want to be in that car. (Laughter)
أريد أن أكون في تلك السيارة. (ضحك)
I want a bigger life.
أريد حياة أكبر.
I want a life beyond this town.
أريد حياة أبعد من هذه البلدة.
I want a life that's out of the ordinary.
أريد حياة استثنائية.
It's my right.
هذا حقي.
It's my right as much as hers.
إنه حقي بقدر أنه حقها.
And so here I am at TED,
ولذلك أنا هنا في TED،
I suppose to tell that story,
ارتأيت أن أروي تلك القصة،
and I think it's appropriate to say the obvious
وأعتقد أنه من المناسب أن نقول ما هو واضح
that there's a symbiotic and intrinsic link
أن هناك علاقة تكافلية وجوهرية
between storytelling and community,
بين رواية القصة والمجتمع،
between community and art,
بين المجتمع والفن،
between community and science and technology,
بين المجتمع والعلوم والتكنولوجيا،
between community and economics.
بين المجتمع والاقتصاد.
It's my belief that
في اعتقادي الخاص أن
abstract economic theory
النظرية الاقتصادية المجردة
that denies the needs of community
التي تنكر احتياجات المجتمع
or denies the contribution that community makes
أو تنفي المساهمة التي يأديها المجتمع
to economy is shortsighted, cruel
للاقتصاد هي نظرية قاصرة وقاسية
and untenable.
وغير مبررة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The fact is, whether you're a rock star
الحقيقة هي أنه سواء كنت نجم روك
or whether you're a welder in a shipyard,
أم كنت عامل لحام في حوض لبناء السفن،
or a tribesman in the upper Amazon,
أم أحد رجال القبائل في الأمازون،
or the queen of England,
أم ملكة إنجلترا،
at the end of the day,
في نهاية المطاف،
we're all in the same boat.
نحن جميعا في نفس القارب.
♪ Aye, the footmen are frantic in their indignation ♪
♪ أجل، الخدم في شدة السخط ♪
♪ You see the queen's took a taxi herself to the station ♪
♪ ترى الملكة تستقل تاكسي بنفسها إلى المحطة ♪
♪ Where the porters, surprised by her lack of royal baggage ♪
♪ بينما يقف الحمالون مندهشين من تواضع متاعها الملكي ♪
♪ Bustle her and three corgis to the rear of the carriage ♪
♪ يستعجلونها وثلاثة من الكلاب إلى مؤخرة العربة ♪
♪ For the train it is crammed with all Europe's nobility ♪
♪ إلى القطار الممتلئ بكل نبلاء أوروبا ♪
♪ And there's none of them famous for their compatibility ♪
♪ ولا أحد منهم مشهور بالتوافقية ♪
♪ There's a fight over seats ♪
♪ هناك عراك حول المقاعد ♪
♪ "I beg pardon, Your Grace ♪
♪ أتوسل اليكِ، جلالتك ♪
♪ But you'll find that one's mine, so get back in your place!" ♪
♪ هذا المقعد لي، لذا عودي الى مكانك ♪
♪ "Aye, but where are they going?" ♪
♪ نعم، ولكن إلى أين هم ذاهبون؟ ♪
♪ All the porters debate ♪
♪ كل الحمالين في حالة نقاش ♪
♪ "Why they're going to Newcastle and they daren't be late ♪
♪ لماذا هم ذاهبون إلى نيوكاسل والويل لهم إن تأخروا ♪
♪ For they're launching a boat on the Tyne at high tide ♪
♪ لأنهم سيدشنون قاربا في تاين عند ارتفاع المد ♪
♪ And they've come from all over, from far and from wide" ♪
♪ وقد أتوا من كل مكان، من كل فج عميق ♪
♪ There's the old Dalai Lama ♪
♪ ذلك هو الدالاي لاما ♪
♪ And the pontiff of Rome ♪
♪ وبابا روما ♪
♪ Every palace in Europe, and there's nay bugger home ♪
♪ من كل قصر في أوروبا ولم يتخلف أحد ♪
♪ There's the Duchess of Cornwall and the loyal Prince of Wales ♪
♪ يوجد دوقة كورنويل وأمير ويلز الأمين ♪
♪ Looking crushed and uncomfortable in his top hat and tails ♪
♪ يبدو مسحوقا وغير مرتاح مرتديا قبعته وذيله ♪
♪ Well, they haven't got tickets ♪
♪ لأنهم لم يحصلوا على تذاكر ♪
♪ Come now, it's just a detail ♪
♪ تعال الآن فهذا لا يهم ♪
♪ There was no time to purchase and one simply has to prevail ♪
♪ لقد نفد الزمن وببساطة لابد أن ننتصر ♪
♪ For we'll get to the shipyards or we'll end up in jail! ♪
♪ لأننا إما أن نصل إلى حوض بناء السفن أو ينتهي بنا الأمر في السجن ♪
♪ When the last ship sails ♪
♪ حينما تبحر آخر سفينة ♪
♪ Oh the roar of the chains ♪
♪ يا هدير السلاسل ♪
♪ And the cracking of timbers ♪
♪ وتشقق الأخشاب ♪
♪ The noise at the end of the world in your ears ♪
♪ تسمع ضجة نهاية العالم في أذنيك ♪
♪ As a mountain of steel makes its way to the sea ♪
♪ كجبل من الصلب يشق طريقه إلى البحر ♪
♪ And the last ship sails ♪
♪ وتبحر آخر سفينة ♪
♪ And whatever you'd promised ♪
♪ أيا كانت الوعود التي قطعتها ♪
♪ Whatever you've done ♪
♪ مهما كان ما قمت به ♪
♪ And whatever the station in life you've become ♪
♪ وأي مرحلة في الحياة قد وصلت ♪
♪ In the name of the Father, in the name of the Son ♪
♪ باسم الرب و باسم الإبن ♪
♪ And no matter the weave of this life that you've spun ♪
♪ وبغض النظر عن نسج هذه الحياة التي نسجت ♪
♪ On the Earth or in Heaven or under the Sun ♪
♪ على الأرض أو في السماء أو تحت الشمس ♪
♪ When the last ship sails ♪
♪ عندما تبحر آخر سفينة ♪
♪ Oh the roar of the chains ♪
♪ يا هدير السلاسل ♪
♪ And the cracking of timbers ♪
♪ وتشقق الأخشاب ♪
♪ The noise at the end of the world in your ears ♪
♪ تسمع ضجة نهاية العالم في أذنيك ♪
♪ As a mountain of steel makes its way to the sea ♪
♪ كجبل من الصلب يشق طريقه الى البحر ♪
♪ And the last ship sails ♪
♪ وتبحر آخر سفينة ♪
Thanks very much for listening to my song.
شكرا جزيلا على استماعكم لأغنيتي
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.
Okay, you have to join in if you know it.
حسنا، لابد أن تشاركوني إن كنتم تعرفونها
(Music) (Applause)
(موسيقى) (تصفيق)
♪ Just a castaway ♪
♪ مجرد شخص منبوذ ♪
♪ An island lost at sea, oh ♪
♪ جزيرة ضائعة في عرض البحر ♪
♪ Another lonely day ♪
♪ يوم آخر من الوحدة ♪
♪ With no one here but me, oh ♪
♪ آه، حيث لا أحد غيري هنا ♪
♪ More loneliness than any man could bear ♪
♪ الكثير من الوحدة أكبرمن أن يتحملها رجل ♪
♪ Rescue me before I fall into despair ♪
♪ أنقذوني قبل أن يتملكني اليأس ♪
♪ I'll send an S.O.S. to the world ♪
♪ سأرسل إشارة استغاثة إلى العالم ♪
♪ I hope that someone gets my ♪
♪ آمل أن يتلقى شخص ما ♪
♪ Message in a bottle ♪
♪ رسالة في قنينة ♪
♪ A year has passed since I wrote my note ♪
♪ عدت سنة منذ أن كتبت مذكرتي ♪
♪ I should have known this right from the start ♪
♪ كان لابد أن أعرف هذا منذ البداية ♪
♪ Only hope can keep me together ♪
♪ الأمل هو كل ما تبقى لي ♪
♪ Love can mend your life ♪
♪ الحب يمكنه إصلاح حياتك ♪
♪ but love can break your heart ♪
♪ ولكنه قادر على تحطيم قلبك ♪
♪ I'll send an S.O.S. to the world ♪
♪ سأرسل رسالة استغاثة إلى العالم ♪
♪ I hope that someone gets my ♪
♪ آمل أن يتلقى شخص ما ♪
♪ Message in a bottle ♪
♪ رسالة في قنينة ♪
♪ Walked out this morning ♪
♪ خارجا هذا الصباح ♪
♪ I don't believe what I saw ♪
♪ لا أصدق ما رأيت ♪
♪ A hundred billion bottles ♪
♪ مئات الملايين من القناني ♪
♪ Washed up on the shore ♪
♪ جرفتها الأمواج على الشاطئ ♪
♪ Seems I'm not alone in being alone ♪
♪ يبدو أني لست وحدي في كوني وحيدا ♪
♪ A hundred billion castaways ♪
♪ مئة مليار من المنبوذين ♪
♪ Looking for a home ♪
♪ يبحثون عن وطن ♪
♪ I'll send an S.O.S. to the world ♪
♪ سأرسل رسالة استغاثة إلى العالم ♪
♪ I hope that someone gets my ♪
♪ آمل أن يتلقى شخص ما ♪
♪ Message in a bottle ♪
♪ رسالة في قنينة ♪
So I'm going to ask you to sing after me,
سأطلب منكم أن تغنوا بعدي،
okay, the next part.
حسنا، الجزء التالي
It's very easy. Sing in unison.
إنه سهل جدا. غنوا بانسجام.
Here we go.
ها نحن نبدأ.
♪ Sending out an S.O.S. ♪ Come on now.
♪ أرسل رسالة استغاثة ♪ هيا الآن.
Audience: ♪ Sending out an S.O.S. ♪
الحضور: ♪ أرسل رسالة استغاثة ♪
Sting: ♪ Sending out an S.O.S. ♪
ستنغ: ♪ أرسل رسالة استغاثة ♪
Sting: ♪ Sending out ♪
ستنغ: ♪ أرسل ♪
♪ Sending out an S.O.S. ♪
♪ أرسل رسالة استغاثة ♪
♪ Yoooooooo ♪
♪ يوووووووووو ♪
Thank you, TED. Goodnight.
شكرا TED، ليلة سعيدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)